<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Raphaël Lemaitre</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/</link><description>Recent content on Raphaël Lemaitre</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 22:15:49 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlemaitre.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pragmatic Programmers on Medium</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/pragmatic-programmers-on-medium/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 22:15:49 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/pragmatic-programmers-on-medium/</guid><description>Good news! The Pragmatic Programmers are on Medium. They publish there their back catalogue. The books can be quite old, but some are still very useful.
The books are mainly aimed to programmers (hence their name 🙂 ), but some can interest non programming people. The full book list can be found here.
A quick selection for non-programmers:
Technical Blogging, Second Edition by Antonio Cangiano Software Estimation Without Guessing by George Dinwiddie Ship It!</description></item><item><title>Hello World!</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 19:27:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time I wanted to have a blog. Writing more and better is one of my goals this year and the blog is a fairly simple way to achieve it.
I will try to write about subjects that interest me: dev, learning, ways to become more efficient (aka productivity), board games and anything else that comes into my mind that deserves to be shared.
What is my blogging platform?</description></item><item><title>whoami</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/whoami/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 14:21:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/whoami/</guid><description>Hi,
I am Raphaël Lemaitre, and it appears you landed on my website.
According to my twitter bio, I am
CTO of @adventori; pragmatic coder; software craftsman; data lover; tech, soccer, golf, food and music enthusiast; proud dad
This sums up well who am I but I&amp;rsquo;ll detail a bit more.
I&amp;rsquo;m a programmer (mainly using JVM languages but not only) living in the Paris area, France. I started working in 2000 and have work mainly for software vendors.</description></item></channel></rss>