<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Raphaël Lemaitre</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Raphaël Lemaitre</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 10:13:20 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlemaitre.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Hacking ADHD – Strategies for the Modern Developer</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2023/11/hacking-adhd-strategies-for-the-modern-developer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 10:13:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2023/11/hacking-adhd-strategies-for-the-modern-developer/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>This article was initially published on &lt;a href="https://www.ledger.com/blog/hacking-adhd-strategies-for-the-modern-developer">Ledger blog&lt;/a>, on November 14th, 2023.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>After struggling a lot with my mental health (anxiety, depressive condition) for several years,
I was diagnosed with Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder, commonly known as ADHD, at the age of 44.
This diagnosis shocked me a lot: I wasn’t a wild child, in fact, I was even a good pupil.
With the help of my therapist, I was able to understand that ADHD can take multiple forms and that it can go undiagnosed until adulthood.
Since then, I’ve been trying many technics to overcome it and make the best of it in my professional life.
This article sums up what I learned so far.&lt;/p></description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This article was initially published on <a href="https://www.ledger.com/blog/hacking-adhd-strategies-for-the-modern-developer">Ledger blog</a>, on November 14th, 2023.</em></p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>After struggling a lot with my mental health (anxiety, depressive condition) for several years,
I was diagnosed with Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder, commonly known as ADHD, at the age of 44.
This diagnosis shocked me a lot: I wasn’t a wild child, in fact, I was even a good pupil.
With the help of my therapist, I was able to understand that ADHD can take multiple forms and that it can go undiagnosed until adulthood.
Since then, I’ve been trying many technics to overcome it and make the best of it in my professional life.
This article sums up what I learned so far.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-adhd">What is ADHD?</h2>
<p><em>Disclaimer: I’m not a psychiatrist nor a neurologist, so this description is surely incomplete</em></p>
<p>ADHD is a neurodevelopmental disorder that affects both children and adults.
According to the American Psychiatric Association’s Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5),
ADHD is characterized by a persistent pattern of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity that interferes with functioning or development.</p>
<p>ADHD manifests differently in individuals:</p>
<ul>
<li>Some people mainly have symptoms of inattention.</li>
<li>Others mostly have symptoms of hyperactivity-impulsivity.</li>
<li>Some have a combination of both.</li>
</ul>
<p>While everybody can occasionally experience some inattention, unfocused motor activity, and impulsivity,
people with ADHD endure more severe and frequent occurrences of these behaviors.
These manifestations can interfere with or reduce the quality of how they function socially, at school, or in a job.</p>

    <img src="/images/blog/adhd/what-is-adhd.webp"  class="center"  style="width: 100%;"  />


<p>Not diagnosing and managing ADHD can lead to a range of complications, including anxiety, burn-out or depression.</p>
<p>It’s not uncommon for ADHD to go undiagnosed until adulthood, as my experience shows.
Many adults discover they have ADHD only after their children are diagnosed, leading them to recognize similar patterns in their own behavior.</p>
<p>Several factors contribute to late diagnosis:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Coping Mechanisms</strong>:
Over the years, adults develop various coping strategies that can mask ADHD symptoms.
For instance, someone might excessively rely on calendars, to-do lists, or alarms to compensate for forgetfulness.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Different Environment</strong>:
The transition from structured educational settings to less structured work environments can reveal hidden ADHD symptoms.
In school, frequent tests and immediate deadlines can actually serve as scaffolding for people with ADHD.
In contrast, long-term projects and self-management in a work environment can expose challenges in planning and sustained focus.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Less Oversight</strong>:
Unlike children, who are constantly observed by teachers and parents, adults generally have less oversight.
This means symptoms can go unnoticed, especially if they don’t manifest as disruptive behavior.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Societal Stigma</strong>:
The stigma surrounding ADHD can discourage people from seeking diagnosis and treatment.
There’s a common misconception that ADHD is a “childhood disorder,” or merely a lack of willpower, which can make adults hesitate to consult healthcare professionals.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Common Misdiagnoses</strong>:
ADHD symptoms can sometimes be misinterpreted as signs of depression or anxiety disorders.
The restlessness and difficulty in focusing associated with ADHD may result in a misdiagnosis, especially if other symptoms like impulsivity are less evident.
A thorough evaluation is crucial for an accurate diagnosis.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="adhd-as-a-double-edged-sword-for-developers">ADHD as a Double-Edged Sword for Developers</h2>
<p>ADHD is often viewed through a negative lens, yet it’s important to acknowledge that the disorder brings not only challenges but also its own set of benefits.</p>

    <img src="/images/blog/adhd/double-edged-sword.webp"  class="center"  style="width: 100%;"  />


<h3 id="benefits">Benefits</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hyperfocus</strong>:
One of the paradoxical advantages of ADHD is the ability to hyperfocus on tasks that you find genuinely interesting or rewarding.
This can be especially beneficial in coding, where being “in the zone” can lead to high levels of productivity.</li>
<li><strong>Creative Problem-Solving</strong>:
The ADHD brain is often highly creative and capable of out-of-the-box thinking, which can be invaluable in software development where novel solutions are often needed.</li>
<li><strong>Quick Adaptation</strong>:
Many people with ADHD thrive in dynamic environments that would overwhelm others.
The rapidly changing nature of technology can therefore be an ideal playground for developers with ADHD.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="challenges">Challenges</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Time Management</strong>:
ADHD can make it difficult to gauge how long a task will take, leading to procrastination and last-minute rushes.
This can be particularly challenging in development projects with tight deadlines.</li>
<li><strong>Organizational Skills</strong>:
Keeping track of multiple codebases, debugging, and even remembering to comment code can be more challenging when you have ADHD.</li>
<li><strong>Consistency</strong>:
While you may excel at certain tasks, the variability in performance can be a concern.
Some days might be incredibly productive, while others are marred by distractions and a lack of focus.</li>
</ul>
<p>Understanding the complexities of ADHD is crucial for adapting your work environment and strategies to leverage its strengths while mitigating its weaknesses.</p>
<h2 id="understanding-the-adhd-brain">Understanding the ADHD brain</h2>

    <img src="/images/blog/adhd/understanding-adhd-brain.webp"  class="center"  style="width: 100%;"  />


<p>When it comes to ADHD, understanding the neurological factors at play can offer valuable insights into managing the condition effectively.
One neurotransmitter that plays a significant role in ADHD is dopamine.
This chemical is responsible for regulating mood, focus, and attention.
In the ADHD brain, dopamine levels are often lower than average, which can result in a constant search for stimulation.</p>
<h3 id="dopamine-and-motivation">Dopamine and Motivation</h3>
<p>“<em>I have motivation issues until I have deadline ones</em>” is how I often describe my relationship with tasks.
Dopamine acts as a motivator, urging us to achieve goals and complete tasks.
However, its scarcity in the ADHD brain means that the urgency often kicks in only when a deadline approaches.
This leads to last-minute rushes that can be either extremely productive or terribly stressful.</p>
<h3 id="hyperfocus">Hyperfocus</h3>
<p>Another common phenomenon among people with ADHD is hyperfocus.
While it may seem counterintuitive, those with ADHD can sometimes focus so intensely on a task that they lose all track of time.
I’ve found myself immersed in tasks, aiming for perfection, to the extent that hours fly by unnoticed.
While this can be an asset in tasks requiring deep concentration, hyperfocus can also become a liability when you neglect other important tasks.</p>
<h3 id="perfectionism">Perfectionism</h3>
<p>In my experience, things must either be perfect or not done at all.
This perfectionism can be attributed, in part, to how the ADHD brain is wired.
We crave the dopamine hit that comes from completing a task perfectly, which often leads us to spend more time on a project than initially planned, fine-tuning every detail.</p>
<p>By recognizing these traits and their underlying neurochemical causes, we can develop strategies and choose the right tools to help us manage our symptoms more effectively.</p>
<h2 id="creating-and-navigating-an-adhd-friendly-work-environment">Creating and navigating an ADHD-friendly work environment</h2>
<p>In a field like software development, where focus and attention to detail are critical, the work environment can either make or break your productivity.
When you have ADHD, crafting an environment that suits your unique cognitive profile is not just beneficial but essential.</p>

    <img src="/images/blog/adhd/adhd-work-environment.webp"  class="center"  style="width: 100%;"  />


<h3 id="setting-up-a-stimulating-workspace">Setting up a Stimulating Workspace</h3>
<p>The ideal workspace for someone with ADHD is not necessarily minimalist or clutter-free.
It’s a space that provides stimulation without becoming distracting.
For me, having multiple monitors has been a game-changer; it allows me to spread out my tasks visibly and switch between them as needed without losing track.</p>
<h3 id="open-office-vs-remote-work-the-adhd-perspective">Open Office vs. Remote Work: The ADHD Perspective</h3>
<p>While the open office layout is often praised for fostering collaboration, it can be a minefield of distractions for someone with ADHD.
Remote work offers the freedom to tailor your environment to your needs but comes with its own set of challenges like isolation.</p>
<h3 id="enter-the-hybrid-setup-the-best-of-both-worlds">Enter the Hybrid Setup: The Best of Both Worlds</h3>
<p>A hybrid work setup can be the golden mean, allowing you the flexibility to work remotely when you need to hunker down and focus,
while also offering the option to come into an office for teamwork and social interaction.
For someone like me, who thrives in different settings depending on the task at hand, this is ideal.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Focus Days</strong>: Choose remote work on days when you need to dive deep into code or take on tasks requiring sustained attention.</li>
<li><strong>Collaboration Days</strong>: Opt for the office environment when the agenda involves brainstorming sessions, team meetings, or project kick-offs.</li>
</ul>
<p>By actively selecting your work environment based on your daily or weekly needs, you take control of your productivity without sacrificing collaboration or focus.</p>
<h3 id="asynchronous-communication">Asynchronous Communication</h3>
<p>Immediate, synchronous communication might be efficient for quick decision-making, but can be a nightmare when you’re trying to focus.
Consider these asynchronous communication methods that give you the time and space to concentrate without constant interruption:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Scheduled Updates</strong>: Replace frequent status meetings with scheduled written updates through platforms like Slack or Microsoft Teams.</li>
<li><strong>Documentation</strong>: Use wikis, shared documents, or tools like Confluence to keep easily accessible and up-to-date information without requiring immediate attention.</li>
<li><strong>Discussion Threads</strong>: Platforms allowing threaded conversations, like Slack threads or forum posts, can let you engage in discussions at your own pace.</li>
<li><strong>Issue Trackers</strong>: Tools like JIRA or GitHub Issues can keep everyone updated without needing a meeting to discuss progress or blockers.</li>
<li><strong>Video Messages</strong>: Recorded video updates are an underrated method for delivering complex information.
Tools like <a href="https://loom.com/">Loom</a> allow you to create quick videos that team members can watch when it best suits them.</li>
<li><strong>Amazon’s Silent Meeting Technique</strong>: Amazon has popularized the “Silent Meeting” approach, where participants read a six-page memo at the start of the meeting in complete silence.
This allows for deep, focused thought before moving on to a discussion.
It’s an excellent way to ensure everyone is on the same page (literally and figuratively) and it respects individual attention spans.</li>
</ul>
<p>By applying these asynchronous methods, you can keep the team in the loop without disrupting your or anyone else’s flow state.</p>
<h3 id="managing-interruptions-in-team-settings">Managing Interruptions in Team Settings</h3>
<p>Interruptions can wreak havoc on anyone’s focus, but they are especially detrimental for people with ADHD.
In my team, we take a flexible approach that allows each individual to manage their own focus time.
Team members are encouraged to block off periods in their calendars, switch off notifications, or do whatever else is necessary to maintain focus during work hours.</p>
<p>To balance the need for individual focus with the benefits of team interaction, we have a standing “Virtual Coffee” appointment every day at 4PM.
Attendance isn’t mandatory, but it’s an open invitation to pause, catch up, and discuss anything from work progress to the latest Netflix series.
This approach fosters a sense of community without imposing on anyone’s focused work time.</p>
<p>By adopting this strategy, we ensure that everyone has the latitude to work in a way that suits their attention span and cognitive style,
while still maintaining the benefits of team cohesion.</p>
<h2 id="self-management-strategies-and-tools-addressing-adhd-symptoms">Self-Management Strategies and Tools: Addressing ADHD Symptoms</h2>

    <img src="/images/blog/adhd/adhd-strategies-and-tools.webp"  class="center"  style="width: 100%;"  />


<p>Navigating ADHD’s unique challenges and benefits has led me to rely on an assortment of tools and strategies that make up my personal tech stack and self-management techniques.
Let’s dive in:</p>
<h3 id="obsidian-the-command-center-for-my-day">Obsidian: The Command Center for My Day</h3>
<p><a href="http://obsidian.md">Obsidian</a> isn’t just a note-taking app for me; it’s the cornerstone of my daily organization.
Here’s how I utilize its capabilities:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Daily Notes</strong>: Every morning, I start my day by planning it out in a custom template that displays my Google Calendar events and Todoist task list.</li>
<li><strong>Jira Integration</strong>: Notes are auto-generated for each Jira ticket I work on, simplifying the process of logging work details.</li>
<li><strong>Google Calendar Integration</strong>: Meeting notes are created automatically for every meeting I attend, keeping me organized.</li>
<li><strong>Readwise &amp; Pocket</strong>: I keep track of book comments and articles-to-read via Readwise and Pocket integrations.</li>
<li><strong>Google Contact</strong>: I can link people I work with in my notes, helping me make connections between tasks and stakeholders.</li>
<li><strong>Other Subjects</strong>: I also make notes on a myriad of other topics (like drafts for this blog post) and link them to my daily note.</li>
<li><strong>End-of-Day Review</strong>: At day’s end, I revisit my daily notes, shifting unfinished tasks and adding any overlooked items.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="time-management-powering-through-with-reclaimai">Time Management: Powering Through with Reclaim.ai</h3>
<p>I swear by <a href="https://reclaim.ai/">Reclaim.ai</a> for managing my time.
It automatically schedules focus time for me—some sessions are ‘protected,’ meaning they can’t be deleted or moved, while others offer more flexibility.
It even blocks out time for lunch and short “decompression” breaks after meetings.</p>
<h3 id="communication-mastering-slack">Communication: Mastering Slack</h3>
<p>I make the most of Slack’s “<a href="https://slack.com/help/articles/208423427-Set-a-reminder#set-a-message-reminder">remind me later</a>” feature.
If I’m in the middle of something and get interrupted by a Slack message, I simply set a reminder to revisit it later.</p>
<h3 id="focus-aid-tuning-in-with-brainfm">Focus Aid: Tuning in with Brain.fm</h3>
<p>When it’s time to hunker down, I turn on <a href="https://brain.fm/">Brain.fm</a>.
I’m even using it right now.
I particularly love the “interval timer” feature, which uses the Pomodoro Technique to alternate between focus time and short breaks.</p>
<p>By employing this tech stack and these strategies, I’ve been able to not just manage, but leverage my ADHD.
Each piece of this puzzle addresses specific symptoms, transforming what some might see as challenges into opportunities for productivity and success.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion-turning-adhd-challenges-into-strengths-in-software-development">Conclusion: Turning ADHD Challenges into Strengths in Software Development</h2>
<p>As someone who was diagnosed with ADHD at 44, I’ve come to appreciate both the struggles and the advantages it brings to my professional life.
By understanding the underlying neurology of ADHD and adopting a targeted set of tools and strategies,
I’ve managed to turn what many perceive as a setback into a unique toolkit for success.
From customized planning and asynchronous communication to harnessing focus and hyperfocus, my journey might resonate with many developers facing similar challenges.</p>
<h3 id="the-importance-of-mental-health">The Importance of Mental Health</h3>
<p>It’s essential to underline the critical role of mental health care.
ADHD can often coexist with other mental health conditions like anxiety or depression, and the toll it takes can be considerable.
Therefore, never hesitate to seek professional help from psychiatrists, psychologists, or therapists.
Your mental well-being is crucial, and experts can provide a structured approach to managing ADHD symptoms.</p>
<p>ADHD isn’t a “one-size-fits-all” condition, but the strategies and tools discussed here can offer a good starting point for software engineers looking to make the most out of their workdays.
Remember, with the right approach and environment, ADHD can be a strength, not just a challenge.</p>
<p><em>Credits: Images generated by <a href="https://openai.com/">OpenAI</a>‘s DALL-E.</em></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>TIL: Trigger a Ci Pipeline From Command Line</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/03/til-trigger-a-ci-pipeline-from-command-line/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 23:10:56 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/03/til-trigger-a-ci-pipeline-from-command-line/</guid><description>&lt;p>At &lt;a href="https://adventori.com/">ADventori&lt;/a>, we use &lt;a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/ci/">Gitlab CI&lt;/a> to deploy our staging environments when code changes in our main branch.
This afternoon, I wanted to re-deploy one of our environments with the same code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One solution I saw was to add a dummy modification to our codebase (for example adding a space in a comment), commit it, and push it to our main branch.
This would trigger our CI/CD pipeline and would result to a new deployment.
This solves my problem, but the code modification is artificial.&lt;/p></description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At <a href="https://adventori.com/">ADventori</a>, we use <a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/ci/">Gitlab CI</a> to deploy our staging environments when code changes in our main branch.
This afternoon, I wanted to re-deploy one of our environments with the same code.</p>
<p>One solution I saw was to add a dummy modification to our codebase (for example adding a space in a comment), commit it, and push it to our main branch.
This would trigger our CI/CD pipeline and would result to a new deployment.
This solves my problem, but the code modification is artificial.</p>
<p>Then, I discovered the <code>--allow-empty</code> option of <code>git commit</code> thanks to this tweet: <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">TIL that you can do `git commit --allow-empty` to make a new commit with no actual changes to your files.<br><br>No more random whitespace changes to trigger new builds! 🥳</p>&mdash; Megan Sullivan (@meganesulli) <a href="https://twitter.com/meganesulli/status/1366466258393161729?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 1, 2021</a></blockquote>
<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

</p>
<p>Eventually, I ran the following command, pushed to our main branch and our staging environment was re-deployed.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>git commit --allow-empty -m <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;Redeploy staging environment&#39;</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div>
    <img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/jS27LWasgUIYrXtP83/giphy.gif"  alt="Job done!"  class="center"  />


]]></content></item><item><title>TIL: Default Heap Configuration in OpenJDK</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/02/til-default-heap-configuration-in-openjdk/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 17:11:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/02/til-default-heap-configuration-in-openjdk/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the first blog post in the &amp;ldquo;Today I learnt&amp;rdquo; (TIL) series.
In this series, as its name suggests, I&amp;rsquo;ll write about random things I learn.
The purpose of all this is to make it easier for me to remember things and, of course, to share it so that others don&amp;rsquo;t struggle to find it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, this afternoon, someone asked me what are the heap configuration of a docker-based tomcat.
We haven&amp;rsquo;t set any particular tomcat configuration, except for our app deployment, so the default one is used.&lt;/p></description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first blog post in the &ldquo;Today I learnt&rdquo; (TIL) series.
In this series, as its name suggests, I&rsquo;ll write about random things I learn.
The purpose of all this is to make it easier for me to remember things and, of course, to share it so that others don&rsquo;t struggle to find it.</p>
<p>So, this afternoon, someone asked me what are the heap configuration of a docker-based tomcat.
We haven&rsquo;t set any particular tomcat configuration, except for our app deployment, so the default one is used.</p>
<p>So, now, the question is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the default heap configuration of an OpenJDK 8 JVM?</p></blockquote>
<p>According to <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/technotes/tools/windows/java.html">Oracle documentation</a>, <em>the default value is chosen at runtime based on system configuration.</em>
It appears it depends on the server architecture, the system memory and the VM type (server or client).</p>
<p>For client configurations, as described in <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/technotes/guides/vm/gctuning/parallel.html#default_heap_size">GC Tuning guide</a>, the default maximum heap size is half of the physical memory up to a physical memory size of 192 megabytes (MB) and otherwise one fourth of the physical memory up to a physical memory size of 1 gigabyte (GB).</p>
<p>For server configurations, as described in <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/technotes/guides/vm/gctuning/ergonomics.html#sthref5">the same guide</a>, the default maximum heap size is 1/4 of the physical memory up to 1 gigabyte for 32-bits JVMs and to 32 gigabytes for 64-bits JVMs.</p>
<p>A simple way to know what is the default value for your JVM on your environment is to run the following command.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>java -XX:+PrintFlagsFinal -version | grep MaxHeapSize
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The result for our JVM inside the docker container is:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text"><span style="display:flex;"><span>    uintx MaxHeapSize                              := 16833839104                         {product}
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>openjdk version &#34;1.8.0_242&#34;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>OpenJDK Runtime Environment (build 1.8.0_242-b08)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>OpenJDK 64-Bit Server VM (build 25.242-b08, mixed mode)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The value is displayed in bytes.
So, here, the default value is 16 GB which is one quarter of the host memory (64 GB).</p>
<p>The <code>java -XX:+PrintFlagsFinal -version</code> command displays a lot of information (several hundreds of parameters), such as the heap space size and the selected garbage collector.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Pragmatic Programmers on Medium</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/02/pragmatic-programmers-on-medium/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 22:15:49 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/02/pragmatic-programmers-on-medium/</guid><description>&lt;p>Good news! The &lt;a href="https://pragprog.com/">Pragmatic Programmers&lt;/a> are on &lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers">Medium&lt;/a>.
They publish there their back catalogue.
The books can be quite old, but some are still very useful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The books are mainly aimed to programmers (hence their name 🙂 ), but some can interest non programming people. The full book list can be found &lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/directory-of-pragmatic-programmer-books-on-medium-6a5cbadbd4b4">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A quick selection for non-programmers:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-10982edb748f">Technical Blogging, Second Edition&lt;/a> by Antonio Cangiano&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-792c48921cbc">Software Estimation Without Guessing&lt;/a> by George Dinwiddie&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-bf557a5592e1">Ship It!&lt;/a> by Jared R. Richardson and William A. Gwaltney Jr.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-ca8ca43c2443">Release It! Second Edition&lt;/a> by Michael T. Nygard&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-667e79ea8e4a">Pomodoro Technique Illustrated&lt;/a> by Staffan Nöteberg&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-42b7d4438ceb">Manage It!&lt;/a> by Johanna Rothman&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-48e7fee28df5">Learn to Program&lt;/a> by Chris Pine&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-67978e9d92fe">Lean from the Trenches&lt;/a> by Henrik Kniberg&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-96ddd6292057">Behind Closed Doors&lt;/a> by Johanna Rothman and Esther Derby&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-e8bf453fe2b4">Become an Effective Software Engineering Manager&lt;/a> by James Stanier&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-9c853b563a92">Creating Great Teams&lt;/a> by Sandy Mamoli and David Mole&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Another selection for programmers:&lt;/p></description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good news! The <a href="https://pragprog.com/">Pragmatic Programmers</a> are on <a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers">Medium</a>.
They publish there their back catalogue.
The books can be quite old, but some are still very useful.</p>
<p>The books are mainly aimed to programmers (hence their name 🙂 ), but some can interest non programming people. The full book list can be found <a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/directory-of-pragmatic-programmer-books-on-medium-6a5cbadbd4b4">here</a>.</p>
<p>A quick selection for non-programmers:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-10982edb748f">Technical Blogging, Second Edition</a> by Antonio Cangiano</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-792c48921cbc">Software Estimation Without Guessing</a> by George Dinwiddie</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-bf557a5592e1">Ship It!</a> by Jared R. Richardson and William A. Gwaltney Jr.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-ca8ca43c2443">Release It! Second Edition</a> by Michael T. Nygard</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-667e79ea8e4a">Pomodoro Technique Illustrated</a> by Staffan Nöteberg</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-42b7d4438ceb">Manage It!</a> by Johanna Rothman</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-48e7fee28df5">Learn to Program</a> by Chris Pine</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-67978e9d92fe">Lean from the Trenches</a> by Henrik Kniberg</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-96ddd6292057">Behind Closed Doors</a> by Johanna Rothman and Esther Derby</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-e8bf453fe2b4">Become an Effective Software Engineering Manager</a> by James Stanier</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-9c853b563a92">Creating Great Teams</a> by Sandy Mamoli and David Mole</li>
</ul>
<p>Another selection for programmers:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-323f1846e259">A Common-Sense Guide to Data Structures and Algorithms, Second Edition</a> by Jay Wengrow</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-1c47dfe47bf">Design It!</a> by Michael Keeling</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-24a9a0d6d60e">Exercises for Programmers</a> by Brian P. Hogan</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-5fe40b18c07a">Explore It!</a> by Elisabeth Hendrickson</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-bd8f1618a58b">Functional Programming in Java</a> by Venkat Subramaniam</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-29add20df224">Java by Comparison</a> by Simon Harrer, Jörg Lenhard, Linus Dietz</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-3134308e7195">Language Implementation Patterns</a> by Terence Parr</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-9e02e42cae02">Learn Functional Programming with Elixir</a> by Ulisses Almeida</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-ad06b9e5f047">Mazes for Programmers</a> by Jamis Buck</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-db1725cc47cd">Modern Vim</a> by Drew Neil</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-2ef01739377f">Practical Microservices</a> by Ethan Garofolo</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-cb11bf75ff3f">Practical Programming, Third Edition</a> by Paul Gries, Jennifer Campbell, and Jason Montojo</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-d7d01025d6ce">Practical Vim, Second Edition</a> by Drew Neil</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-3db54fa4761d">Pragmatic Scala</a> by Venkat Subramaniam</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-237ed2475b2e">Pragmatic Version Control</a> by Travis Swicegood</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-e77064623b93">Programming Groovy 2</a> by Venkat Subramaniam</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-1d85cc6347c0">Programming Kotlin</a> by Venkat Subramaniam</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-8fffbe0b7b6d">Rediscovering JavaScript</a> by Venkat Subramaniam</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-1eec0e33001">Remote Pairing</a> by Joe Kutner</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-5c00bfd17aa6">Seven Concurrency Models in Seven Weeks</a> by Paul Butcher</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-f3cb9ada3c82">Seven Databases in Seven Weeks, Second Edition</a> by Luc Perkins, with Eric Redmond, and Jim R. Wilson</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-bf907a514a34">Seven Languages in Seven Weeks</a> by Bruce A. Tate</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-640644b1fe02">Seven More Languages in Seven Weeks</a> by Bruce A. Tate, Fred Daoud, Ian Dees, and Jack Moffitt</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-d5ed3e0ac475">Seven Mobile Apps in Seven Weeks</a> by Tony Hillerson</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-792c48921cbc">Software Estimation Without Guessing</a> by George Dinwiddie</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-bfed08449866">The Developer’s Code</a> by Ka Wai Cheung</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-23a75c7cba86">The Healthy Programmer</a> by Joe Kutner</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-49d578099203">The Passionate Programmer</a> by Chad Fowler</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pragmatic-programmers/table-of-contents-622967a31cb9">Your Code as a Crime Scene</a> by Adam Tornhill</li>
</ul>
<p>I think I&rsquo;ll start with The Healthy Programmer, it should be a good read during these time of global pandemic.</p>
<p>What about you?
Did you read one of these books?
Was it good?
Which one will you read next?
Please tell me in the comments.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Hello World!</title><link>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/02/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 19:27:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://rlemaitre.com/posts/2021/02/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time I wanted to have a blog.
Writing more and better is one of my goals this year and the blog is a fairly simple way to achieve it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will try to write about subjects that interest me: dev, learning, ways to become more efficient (aka productivity), board games and anything else that comes into my mind that deserves to be shared.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-my-blogging-platform">What is my blogging platform?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Once I decided to create this blog, once I found the subjects to write about, I had to find out how to do it.
I had several possibilities to do so:&lt;/p></description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a long time I wanted to have a blog.
Writing more and better is one of my goals this year and the blog is a fairly simple way to achieve it.</p>
<p>I will try to write about subjects that interest me: dev, learning, ways to become more efficient (aka productivity), board games and anything else that comes into my mind that deserves to be shared.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-my-blogging-platform">What is my blogging platform?</h2>
<p>Once I decided to create this blog, once I found the subjects to write about, I had to find out how to do it.
I had several possibilities to do so:</p>
<ul>
<li>Write posts on <a href="https://medium.com/@rlemaitre">Medium</a></li>
<li>Write posts on <a href="https://dev.to/rlemaitre">dev.to</a></li>
<li>Hosting a blog using <a href="https://wordpress.com/">wordpress</a></li>
<li>Use a static site generator and host it on <a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pages/">Gitlab</a> or <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Being very attached to data protection and confidentiality (on a personal basis, I try to use as little google as possible, I will surely come back to this in a future article), I have chosen not to use a third party service as my main publication platform.
I&rsquo;m a dev, the choice of the static site generator with articles written in Markdown, and a hosting based on Git was thus naturally imposed to me.
This solution even guarantees better durability over time, <a href="https://brandur.org/fragments/graceful-degradation-time">as written by @brandur</a>.
I turned to <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/rhazdon/hugo-theme-hello-friend-ng">Hello Friend NG</a> theme of <a href="https://atlialp.com/">Djordje Atlialp</a>.</p>
<p>The source of this site is hosted on a <a href="https://github.com/rlemaitre/rlemaitre.github.io">Github repository</a>.
Do not hesitate to create <a href="https://github.com/rlemaitre/rlemaitre.github.io/issues">an issue</a> or a <a href="https://github.com/rlemaitre/rlemaitre.github.io/pulls">pull request</a> if you see any bug or typo.</p>
<p>As this theme allows me to have the site and the blog written in several languages, I will try to write as much as possible my articles <a href="/fr/posts/">in French</a> and <a href="/posts/">in English</a>.</p>
<p>I wanted to have a comment system on the blog. However, because of <a href="https://supunkavinda.blog/disqus">data protection issues</a>, I didn&rsquo;t want to use disqus.
I turned to <a href="https://utteranc.es/">Utterances</a> which is open source, without any tracking and stores comments as GitHub issues.
So don&rsquo;t hesitate to comment on articles, you just need to have a GitHub account to do so.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>✍️ Edit 16/02/2021: Add link to <a href="https://github.com/rlemaitre/rlemaitre.github.io">Github repository</a>.</em></p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>